Welcome back everyone. Today Pat and I will be reviewing an online session you played with pretty high stakes.
여러분 환영합니다. 오늘 팻과 함께 꽤 높은 스테이크에서 플레이한 온라인 세션을 리뷰하겠습니다.
What do you have for us here, brother?
준비한 게 뭔가요, 브라더?
Table 1 is $150 on GG. Table 2 is a $2k/$4k big game. Table 3 is a $215 MTT. Then a $1k Thrill, a $630, and a $54.
테이블 1은 GG $150입니다. 테이블 2는 $2k/$4k 빅 게임이고요. 테이블 3은 $215 MTT입니다. 그리고 $1k Thrill, $630, $54가 있습니다.
Cool. Let's jump in. Immediately we see you playing a big pot with AQ. Remember the action?
좋네요. 바로 시작하죠. AQ으로 큰 팟을 플레이하는 게 보이네요. 액션 기억하시나요?
Pre-flop we open 2BB, he 3-bets to 10BB.
프리플랍에 2BB 오픈했고, 상대가 10BB로 3-bet 했습니다.
What do you think pre-flop? What does your red dot mean?
프리플랍은 어떻게 생각하세요? 그 빨간 점은 무슨 뜻인가요?
It marks a 'red line' player. I think the decision is easy versus a red line guy. Clear call. I'd fold versus nits.
"레드 라인" 플레이어라는 뜻입니다. 레드 라인 상대를 상대로는 결정이 쉽습니다. 클리어 콜이죠. 타이트한 플레이어 상대로는 폴드했을 겁니다.
For those watching, 2BB to 10BB against general population is an easy fold. But against a good aggressive reg?
시청자분들을 위해 설명하자면, 일반적인 풀을 상대로 2BB에서 10BB는 쉬운 폴드입니다. 하지만 잘하는 어그레시브 레귤러라면요?
A red line player has a high win rate without showdown. They are aggressive and have appropriate bluffs.
레드 라인 플레이어는 쇼다운 없는 승률이 높습니다. 그들은 어그레시브하고 적절한 블러프를 가지고 있죠.
Good point. So they make it 10BB, you call. Pot size indicates they c-bet a quarter and you called?
좋은 지적이네요. 그래서 10BB로 레이즈하고 콜했습니다. 팟 사이즈를 보니 상대가 1/4 팟 c-bet을 했고 콜하셨네요?
Yeah, c-bet a quarter. Decision on the turn now. What do you think about turn with AQ?
네, 1/4 c-bet이었습니다. 이제 턴 결정입니다. AQ으로 턴을 어떻게 생각하시나요?
One of the worst hands we land with. Opponent plays Kx this way, but also plays hands that beat us that might fold now or later.
여기서 우리가 가질 수 있는 최악의 핸드 중 하나입니다. 상대는 Kx로 이렇게 플레이하지만, 우리를 이기고 있는 핸드들도 나중에 폴드할 수 있습니다.
I'm torn on whether to bluff. Lean towards bluffing?
블러프를 할지 고민되네요. 블러프 쪽으로 기우나요?
If you're torn, it's close. If you lean bluff every time, you aren't losing much EV.
고민된다면 가까운 결정입니다. 매번 블러프 쪽으로 기울어도 EV 손실은 크지 않을 겁니다.
Here, it's important not to block hands like QQ♥️ calling turn and folding river, rather than blocking flushes.
여기서는 플러시를 블락하는 것보다, 턴에 콜하고 리버에 폴드할 QQ♥️ 같은 핸드를 블락하지 않는 게 중요합니다.
AQ without a ♥️ becomes a good triple barrel.
♥️가 없는 AQ은 좋은 트리플 배럴 후보가 됩니다.
Tough. I have QJs. Don't have AJo pre. Most bluffs will be AQ, 65s, 54s. Struggling for bluffs.
어렵네요. 전 QJs이 있습니다. 프리플랍에 AJo는 없고요. 대부분의 블러프는 AQ, 65s, 54s가 될 겁니다. 블러프 레인지가 부족하네요.
We have 15 combos of AQ bluffs. We have TT for value. Probably play AA this way too. Just thinking if we are over-bluffing.
우린 AQ 블러프 15 콤보가 있습니다. 밸류를 위한 TT도 있고요. 아마 AA도 이렇게 플레이할 겁니다. 오버 블러핑이 아닌지 생각 중입니다.
Yeah, that's a big point. Sometimes it's the best option to overbluff.
네, 중요한 포인트입니다. 가끔은 오버 블러핑이 최선의 선택일 때가 있죠.
I 100% agree. If you're in this spot, always shove AA here versus almost anyone when they make it 10bb.
100% 동의합니다. 이 상황에서 상대가 10bb로 만들면 거의 누구를 상대로든 항상 AA로 올인해야 합니다.
The solver might slow play, but don't do it. Just always shove AA, always shove KK.
솔버는 슬로우 플레이할 수도 있지만, 그러지 마세요. 그냥 항상 AA, KK로 올인하세요.
When the option's close, and bluffing small is really good, just always take that bluffing small option.
옵션이 비슷할 때 작게 블러핑하는 게 좋다면, 항상 그 작은 블러핑 옵션을 선택하세요.
We don't need to bet big to get AT♠️ or JJ without a ♥️ to fold.
AT♠️나 ♥️가 없는 JJ을 폴드시키기 위해 크게 베팅할 필요는 없습니다.
Yeah, and I think there is a ton of EV in betting turn.
네, 그리고 turn 베팅에는 엄청난 EV가 있다고 생각합니다.
I think the turn is mandatory because of the Tx and the JJ with no heart.
Tx와 하트 없는 JJ 때문에 turn 베팅은 필수라고 생각합니다.
But then the question is: do we follow through or not?
하지만 문제는 '계속 공격할 것인가, 말 것인가'입니다.
Looks like you're going third and not quarter? You rewound the hand.
쿼터 대신 서드(1/3) 베팅을 하셨네요? 핸드를 되감으셨군요.
Yeah, I wanted to get the earliest street. I went 8.5bb.
네, 가장 초기 스트리트를 보고 싶었어요. 8.5bb로 베팅했습니다.
So 8.5bb is going to be a mandatory call versus most players.
8.5bb는 대부분의 플레이어를 상대로 필수적인 콜이 되겠네요.
Checking who he is might not change my pre-flop decision with AQ, but it sets my mindset for the hand.
빌런이 누구인지 확인하는 게 AQ 프리플랍 결정은 안 바꾸더라도, 핸드 전체의 마인드셋을 잡아줍니다.
He went third instead of quarter, which makes sense based on the smaller pre-flop raise.
상대도 쿼터 대신 서드를 썼는데, 프리플랍 레이즈가 작았던 걸 고려하면 말이 됩니다.
But I don't think it changes our decision tree. We still call flop and bet turn.
하지만 의사결정 트리가 바뀐다고 생각진 않아요. 여전히 flop은 콜, turn은 벳할 핸드죠.
It's just information for later. It doesn't change the decision immediately.
나중을 위한 정보일 뿐, 당장의 결정을 바꾸지는 않습니다.
I wouldn't like betting turn then giving up river. Either bet turn and follow through, or check turn.
전 turn에 베팅하고 river를 포기하는 건 싫어요. turn에 베팅하고 계속 밀거나, 체크해야죠.
Oh, you don't like shutting down?
아, 도중에 멈추는 걸 싫어하시는군요?
I never shut down. Once he checks twice, you get good bluffing opportunities.
절대 안 멈추죠. 상대가 두 번 체크하면 좋은 블러핑 기회가 생깁니다.
The more a range checks, the more likely it is to fold.
레인지가 체크를 많이 할수록, 폴드할 확률도 높아집니다.
When he bets flop and checks twice, 99 is always in that range.
상대가 flop에 벳하고 두 번 체크하면, 99는 항상 그 레인지에 있습니다.
When we bet turn, that range still has AA and AK.
우리가 turn에 베팅할 때, 그 레인지에는 여전히 AA와 AK가 있습니다.
You strip the strong hands when he double checks.
상대가 더블 체크하면 강한 핸드는 제외됩니다.
It's important to point out that 99 are not in this range for a lot of players.
많은 플레이어들의 레인지에 99가 없다는 점을 지적하는 게 중요합니다.
Neither is ATs, neither is AJ.
ATs도 없고, AJ도 없습니다.
A strong argument can be made for folding against players who are massively under 3-bet.
3-bet 빈도가 매우 낮은 플레이어를 상대로는 폴드해야 한다는 강력한 주장이 가능하죠.
And the speed of the 3-bet. When playing 6 tables, I really watch timing.
3-bet 속도도 중요합니다. 6개 테이블을 돌릴 땐 타이밍을 유심히 봅니다.
If he has A5s, he thinks 'do I flat or 3-bet?'. If he has AK, he just 3-bets.
A5s라면 '플랫할까 3-bet할까' 고민하겠죠. AK라면 바로 3-bet할 겁니다.
We ran into AK, which doesn't say much about my bluff really.
AK를 만났는데, 제 블러핑에 대해 많은 걸 말해주진 않네요.
It only says a lot if he calls with AT♠️.
상대가 AT♠️로 콜했다면 제 블러핑에 대해 많은 걸 시사했겠죠.
So you limp AA, 100bb deep on table 1. Let's talk about limping theory.
1번 테이블에서 100bb 딥으로 AA 림프를 하셨네요. 림프 이론에 대해 얘기해보죠.
From a GTO perspective, it wants more limps at 100bb deep stack depth.
GTO 관점에서는 100bb 딥 스택일 때 더 많은 림프를 원합니다.
...the positional disadvantage, that's again from a theoretical perspective,
...포지션의 불리함은 이론적인 관점에서 볼 때,
against weaker opponents who are going to overfold post-flop.
포스트 플랍에서 오버폴드하는 약한 상대를 대상으로 합니다.
I'm a big, big fan of having a very high SB raise, just 'cause I think they play so bad.
저는 SB에서 매우 크게 레이즈하는 것을 정말 좋아합니다. 그들이 너무 못한다고 생각하기 때문이죠.
I think people overfold to it, they overfold flop, therefore you're profiting a lot.
사람들이 거기에 오버폴드하고, 플랍에서도 오버폴드해서 수익이 많이 납니다.
You also don't get limp 3-bet bluffed by an average guy.
또한 평범한 플레이어에게 림프 3-bet 블러프를 당할 일도 없죠.
They don't limp 76s and then 3-bet.
그들은 76s로 림프하고 3-bet 하지 않으니까요.
I'll take that raising, I'm doing the SB.
그럼 저는 레이즈 할게요. 제가 SB라고 하죠.
Oh from the SB? Yeah, yeah, sure.
아, SB에서요? 네, 그럼요.
Well, it works both ways, like people are too passive in position and out of position.
사람들이 인 포지션이나 아웃 오브 포지션에서 모두 너무 패시브해서 양쪽 다 통하죠.
Just do something aggressive blind versus blind and it's going to work well.
블라인드 대 블라인드(BvB)에서 공격적으로 하면 잘 통할 겁니다.
And this is actually the spot you're talking about when you're in the BB and SB limps...
이건 당신이 BB에 있고 SB가 림프할 때의 상황인데요,
...is actually something Chrissy recently talked about where like in early stages at really deep stacks, if the SB limps,
Chrissy가 최근에 말한 내용인데, 초반 딥스택 구간에서 SB가 림프하면,
she just raises and doesn't really care if she gets called because of the fold frequency post-flop is high enough...
그녀는 콜을 받든 말든 그냥 레이즈합니다. 포스트 플랍 폴드 빈도가 충분히 높아서...
...that like she's just winning a bigger pot on average.
...평균적으로 더 큰 팟을 가져갈 수 있기 때문이죠.
And so attacking like the capped range, those weaker ranges that limp-call...
그래서 림프-콜하는 캡된 레인지와 약한 레인지를 공격하는 것이...
...when people are unbalanced is just going to turn a really nice profit.
...상대가 언밸런스할 때 정말 좋은 수익을 낼 수 있습니다.
So back to the decision at hand, what sizing do you like here and why?
그럼 이번 결정으로 돌아와서, 여기서 어떤 사이즈를 선호하시나요?
Well I think when I'm playing a $150 tournament, there's two things that I ask myself straight away:
$150 토너먼트를 할 때 저는 바로 두 가지를 자문합니다.
Who is the opponent and what does my hand want to do?
빌런은 누구인가? 그리고 내 핸드는 무엇을 원하는가?
Who is the opponent? What does my hand want to do? AA wants to get lots of money in pre-flop.
빌런은 누구인가? 내 핸드는 무엇을 원하는가? AA는 프리플랍에 많은 돈을 넣고 싶어 합니다.
So what's the best way to do that?
그럼 가장 좋은 방법은 무엇일까요?
Um, in general, if I'm limping AA, it's versus someone that is going to do the Chrissy B thing, right?
보통 제가 AA로 림프한다면, 그건 Chrissy B 전략을 쓰는 사람을 상대로 할 때입니다.
That's going to raise 85o 100% frequency.
85o로 100% 빈도로 레이즈하는 사람 말이죠.
That way, like they're going to put 3.5 bigs in and then we want to check-raise to really big sizing.
그렇게 하면 상대가 3.5bb를 넣을 테니, 그때 우리가 아주 크게 체크-레이즈 하는 겁니다.
Cause we want to now get... 85o is going to fold whatever, but we want to get the maximum versus JTs or whatever.
우리는... 85o는 어차피 폴드하겠지만, JTs 같은 핸드를 상대로 맥시멈 밸류를 뽑고 싶으니까요.
Versus a range that wants to see a flop, you want to charge that range a lot of money cause it's not going to 4-bet.
플랍을 보고 싶어 하는 레인지를 상대로는 비싸게 불러야 합니다. 어차피 4-bet 하지 않을 테니까요.
He's never going to 4-bet a bluff here, he's just going to see a flop.
여기서 블러프로 4-bet 할 리는 없고, 그냥 플랍을 보려 할 겁니다.
So in those instances it's very good to go big with value.
그런 경우에는 밸류를 위해 크게 가는 게 좋습니다.
When your range is kind of polarized, the other person is incentivized to call.
당신의 레인지가 폴라라이즈되어 있으면 상대는 콜하고 싶어지죠.
That's... when your polarity increases, your sizing generally wants to increase with it...
폴라리티가 커질수록 사이즈도 키워야 합니다.
...cause you're not interested in seeing a flop, if that makes sense. So really nice big check-raise sizing.
우린 플랍을 보는 데 관심이 없으니까요. 그래서 아주 큰 체크-레이즈 사이즈가 좋습니다.
The absolute smallest I think we should go here is like 13 to 14.
여기서 절대적으로 가장 작은 사이즈는 13~14bb 정도라고 봅니다.
I could definitely see logic for going larger.
더 크게 갈 논리도 충분히 있고요.
I think I went 15... I gave the AA discount.
저는 15bb로 했던 것 같아요... AA 할인을 좀 해줬죠.
You gotta just give him a little bit of rope keeping in.
상대가 들어올 여지를 조금 줘야 하니까요.
That's why I thought about 13 or 14 cause you have that AA discount because like, yeah, you're looking for action.
그래서 저도 13이나 14를 생각했어요. AA 할인을 줘서 액션을 유도해야 하니까요.
13.9 or something, 13.99 for a little discount.
13.9 정도나, 13.99로 약간 할인해 주는 거죠.
Yeah, I'm in for it.
네, 찬성입니다.
Let's see what I do. I go... okay, I go pretty big. I go big and chunky.
제가 뭘 했는지 보죠. 아... 꽤 크게 갔네요. 아주 묵직하게 갔습니다.
But yeah, just always asking myself, who is the villain and what does my hand want to do?
하지만 항상 자문합니다. 빌런은 누구고 내 핸드는 무엇을 원하는가?
So if it's a passive guy, I would just raise 7x there because he's not going to 3-bet me...
패시브한 사람이라면 그냥 7x로 레이즈 할 겁니다. 3-bet 하지 않을 테고...
...and he's going to call JTs whatever I do. So just target the inelastic continues kind of.
...JTs로 제가 뭘 하든 콜할 테니까요. 비탄력적인 콜 범위를 타겟팅하는 거죠.
If you go 3.5x with AA, that's kind of the only money that's going in there unless he has JJ, TT, QQ.
AA로 3.5x만 하면, 상대가 JJ, TT, QQ를 가지고 있지 않는 한 팟이 커지지 않습니다.
They 3-bet if you go 7 anyway, so you're just guaranteeing money gets in there.
어차피 7x로 해도 그런 핸드들은 3-bet 할 테니, 돈을 확실히 넣게 만드는 게 낫죠.
Yeah, definitely.
네, 확실히 그렇습니다.
Um, now let's talk about table three. We're UTG, jams 8-handed for 7bb.
자, 테이블 3으로 가보죠. 우리는 UTG이고, 8핸드에서 7bb 올인 상황입니다.
We have ATs. What are your like thought process here?
핸드는 ATs입니다. 어떤 사고 과정을 거치시나요?
Um, who is villain and what does my hand want to do?
빌런은 누구고 내 핸드는 무엇을 원하는가? 저는 그냥 폴드하고 싶네요.
I think I just want to fold here.
이 레인지에는 우리가 도미네이트하는 핸드가 별로 없어요.
Um, this range shouldn't have many hands that we dominate in it.
A9o가 레이즈-폴드 할 수 있는데, 그게 유일하죠. 뒤에 5명이나 남았고요.
As in A9o can raise-fold, that's the only one. And there's 5 stacks behind.
네, 하지만 A9o가 레이즈-폴드 할 수도 있지만, 그냥 올인할 수도 있지 않을까요?
Yeah, but like, A9o could raise-fold, but will it raise-fold or will it just shove?
AJ, AK, AQ는 항상 올인하겠죠... 그들이 우리를 도미네이트합니다.
AJ, AK, AQ always shove... they dominate.
네. 하지만 약한 Ax 콤보로 너무 많이 올인하는 플레이어들이...
Yeah. I would say that like there is a certain percentage of the population who just jams way too many of their weak Ax combos here...
...분명히 존재하고, 7bb 상황에서 너무 넓게 올인하곤 합니다. 그래서 상대가 누구인지가 중요하죠.
...and is just jamming too wide for 7. And so, you know, who is my opponent is naturally a very good first question.
하지만 이 상황은 정말 아슬아슬하네요.
But I think this one's extremely close.
하나 덧붙이자면, 만약 상황이 비슷하고 제가 30bb를 가지고 있어서...
One thing, if it's close, like let's say I have 30bb here and I can call-fold to everyone behind.
...뒤에 있는 모두에게 콜-폴드 할 수 있다면 다르겠지만, 스택의 3분의 1은 꽤 큰 타격이죠.
I don't know.
모르겠네요.
So 9 off the money, I think better to just... if I'm not sure, just put zero in.
머니인까지 9명 남았다면, 확실하지 않을 땐 그냥 0으로 두는 게 낫겠어요.
Oh, 9 off the money? See, that's an incredibly important factor.
아, 머니인까지 9명이라고요? 그건 정말 중요한 요소네요.
You're 18 off the money. 79 left, 61 pay. It makes it significantly closer when there's this much ICM.
머니인까지 18명 남았군요. 79명 생존, 61명 머니인. ICM 압박이 심해서 훨씬 타이트해지겠네요.
Players are going to shove tighter, chips in our stack are much more valuable than they are otherwise.
플레이어들은 더 타이트하게 올인할 거고, 우리 스택의 칩 가치는 평소보다 훨씬 높습니다.
So what if you're in the first 40% of a tournament?
그럼 토너먼트 초반 40% 구간이라면 어떨까요?
Oh, we gambling. We getting our gambling shoes on.
오, 그럼 도박해야죠. 도박 모드로 갑니다.
Your range is strong enough here where you probably don't want to have that many call folds. You're not looking to VPIP tons of hands here.
여기서 당신의 레인지는 충분히 강해서 콜 폴드를 많이 하고 싶진 않을 겁니다. VPIP를 너무 높이려 하지 마세요.
So you have enough traps in your calling range that you're comfortable calling. Maybe if we flat here, AQ hero folds?
콜링 레인지에 트랩이 충분하니 콜하기 편하죠. 여기서 콜하면 AQ은 히어로 폴드할까요?
Yeah, I think call is better as well. But it is worth noting that if someone jams the CO and you have ATs on the BTN, it's going to be a re-jam.
네, 저도 콜이 낫다고 봅니다. 하지만 CO가 올인하고 BTN에서 ATs를 들고 있다면 리잼해야 한다는 점은 주목할 만하죠.
Just a close spot, I'll keep my 20 BBs and operate. I'd prefer to do that.
아슬아슬한 상황이니 그냥 20 BB를 지키며 운영하겠습니다. 그게 낫겠어요.
So, assuming you fold. Are you gonna fold? You can just tell us and we can go to the other hand here.
그럼 폴드한다고 치고. 폴드하실 건가요? 그냥 말씀해 주세요.
I thought I'd keep the suspense. No, I just fold, yeah.
긴장감을 좀 주려고 했죠. 네, 그냥 폴드합니다.
So I'm going to go back to this Q5♥️ hand.
그럼 Q5♥️ 핸드로 돌아가 보겠습니다.
MP opens, SB calls, we overcall Q5s.
MP 오픈, SB 콜, 우리는 Q5s로 오버콜.
It comes nothing for us. The turn is an A♥️ after it checks through. And what are your thoughts on leading versus checking?
플랍은 아무것도 안 맞았고 첵 굿. 턴에 A♥️가 떨어졌습니다. 동크와 체크 중 어떤 게 낫나요?
I think a lot of people will just think like 'Oh I have a flush draw I have to lead'.
많은 사람들이 '오 플러시 드로우네, 동크해야지'라고 생각할 것 같아요.
I don't see much fold equity here. The way Q5 makes its EV is once in position checks back and says I don't have QJ or KJ, I have 66.
여기서 폴드 에퀴티가 별로 없어 보입니다. Q5가 EV를 만드는 방식은 인포지션이 첵백하면서 '난 QJ이나 KJ 없어, 66이야'라고 하는 것과 같아요.
At the moment I'm attacking two ranges that still have Jx.
지금 저는 여전히 Jx를 가진 두 레인지를 공격하고 있는 겁니다.
If I check the turn, I can hit my flush or I can bluff with more info. Delaying this hand till the river makes a lot of sense.
턴에 체크하면 플러시를 띄우거나 더 많은 정보로 블러프할 수 있죠. 리버까지 미루는 게 합리적입니다.
Yeah, and I do think it's a spot where people make the mistake of just leading turn because they have equity. I don't think you're gonna get folds often enough.
맞아요. 에퀴티가 있다고 턴에 동크하는 실수를 하죠. 폴드를 충분히 받아내지 못할 겁니다.
It comes back to that thing: what does my hand want to do? Q5 wants to see a river for really good bluffing spots and it wants to realize.
결국 내 핸드가 뭘 하고 싶은지로 귀결됩니다. Q5는 좋은 블러프 스팟을 위해 리버를 보고 싶고, 에퀴티를 실현하고 싶어 하죠.
Have I called the river here? You did call the river here.
제가 리버에 콜했나요? 네, 리버에 콜하셨습니다.
I didn't see him value betting 88... And I thought a Jack would bet the turn really often.
상대가 88로 밸류 벳할 거라곤 안 봤고... 잭이라면 턴에 벳했을 거라 생각했어요.
So sometimes we lose to J9s, J8s, JTs. But there's K-highs, 98s. There's enough bluffs in there I think.
J9s, J8s, JTs에는 지겠지만, K하이, 98s 같은 것도 있잖아요. 블러프가 충분히 섞여 있다고 봅니다.
I was actually really just surprised to see his exact hand. He showed you a full house bro.
상대 핸드 보고 정말 놀랐어요. 풀하우스를 보여주던데요.
If he value bet 99, well played. I just wouldn't expect it.
99로 밸류 벳했다면 잘한 거죠. 예상 못 했을 뿐.
But we saved the whole stack mate, we saved 4 BBs back.
그래도 우리 스택은 지켰잖아요. 4 BB는 건졌습니다.
Do you think people have the mental aspect of 'well my hand could have bet the turn so it's okay if I lose a bet anyway'?
사람들이 '내 핸드로 턴에 벳할 수도 있었으니 어차피 벳 하나 잃어도 괜찮아'라고 합리화할까요?
No, I think people have the mental aspect of they need to win the pot rather than make the maximum EV decision.
아뇨, 사람들은 최대 EV 결정을 내리기보다 당장 팟을 이겨야 한다는 강박이 있는 것 같아요.
You checking the turn there will make more money for Q5♥️ but you'll lose the pot more often. It's a very strange paradox.
턴에 체크하면 Q5♥️로 돈은 더 벌겠지만 팟은 더 자주 잃게 되죠. 참 묘한 역설입니다.
I can just call the river.
그냥 리버에 콜만 해도 돼요.
There is definitely some logic to it. I kind of thought that way before.
확실히 일리 있는 말이에요. 저도 예전엔 그렇게 생각했거든요.
I could see people making that mistake where, let's say 66 checks back...
사람들이 그런 실수를 하는 게 이해가 돼요. 66가 체크 백한다고 치면...
...and someone leads the river. They think 'I would've lost if I c-bet anyway, so I can call 66.'
...상대가 리버에 동크를 할 때 '어차피 c-bet 했어도 졌을 테니 66로 콜할 수 있어'라고 생각하죠.
But with 66, you're not putting the right amount of money in the pot, so it can't be that bad.
하지만 66로는 핸드 가치에 맞는 돈을 팟에 넣지 않았으니 그리 나쁜 건 아니겠죠.
If you were meant to lose this bet, it can't be too bad, I think.
어차피 질 벳이었다면, 크게 나쁠 건 없다고 봐요.
But that's the mental issue. We mentally trick ourselves into making mistakes.
그게 바로 멘탈 문제예요. 스스로를 속여서 실수하게 만드는 거죠.
So you defend J6o here versus UTG+1?
그럼 여기서 UTG+1 상대로 J6o를 방어하나요?
Yeah. I think the vast majority of people are just gonna fold this pre-flop.
네. 아마 대다수의 사람들은 프리플랍에 폴드할 거예요.
All charts are 2.2x or 2.3x at 36BB. None of them are min-raise.
모든 차트가 36BB에서 2.2x나 2.3x를 추천해요. 민 레이즈는 없죠.
Also, something happens with the 6 because most of his range is Ace high.
그리고 6가 있으면 상대 레인지 대부분인 A 하이 상대로 뭔가 효과가 있어요.
With the 6, hands like K6s flat 4-bets because of the 2-3-4-5 effect.
6가 있으면 2-3-4-5 효과 때문에 K6s 같은 핸드로 4-bet에 콜하게 되죠.
I'd fold J5o and call J6o. But it's very marginal.
전 J5o는 폴드하고 J6o는 콜하겠어요. 아주 마지널한 차이입니다.
Fair enough. Playing 6 tables, I take any small edge. At 10 tables, I fold this.
맞아요. 6테이블에선 작은 엣지도 챙기지만, 10테이블이라면 폴드할 겁니다.
That's an easy spot to miss with K8o. That's a pure call for 4BB.
K8o는 놓치기 쉬운 스팟이에요. 4BB라면 무조건 콜이죠.
I don't know about that. What's the stack depth there?
글쎄요. 스택 깊이가 얼마나 되죠?
Why is this a pure call? I would always fold this.
왜 무조건 콜이라고 생각하죠? 전 항상 폴드했거든요.
Run it in HRC. I used to fold too, but with money in the SB getting 3 to 1...
HRC로 돌려보세요. 저도 예전엔 폴드했지만, SB에 돈이 들어갔고 3대1 배당이라면...
Sometimes the original raiser shoves and it gets heads up.
원래 레이즈한 사람이 올인해서 헤즈업이 되기도 하고요.
Also with 4BB, I'm looking for any reason to gamble.
게다가 4BB밖에 없을 땐 도박을 걸 이유를 찾게 되죠.
I can't reach the prize pool, I don't cover anyone. In PSKOs, you want to gamble when short.
상금권은 멀었고 누구도 커버하지 못하죠. PSKO에서 숏스택일 땐 최대한 도박을 해야 해요.
Keep in mind, your decision would change if registration wasn't still open.
기억하세요. 만약 등록이 마감된 상태라면 결정이 달라질 겁니다.
Not gonna lie, in a $55 game I'm more incentivized to gamble than in a 10k.
솔직히 1만 달러 게임보다 55달러 게임에서 좀 더 도박을 걸고 싶어지죠.
The truth comes out. It's still a call. You should call way wider than people do.
본심이 나오네요. 그래도 여전히 콜입니다. 사람들 생각보다 훨씬 넓게 콜해야 해요.
At 4-5 BBs when covered, find any excuse to gamble or you make no money.
4-5BB이고 테이블 전체가 날 커버한다면 도박할 핑계를 찾아야 해요. 안 그러면 돈을 못 법니다.
Table 4, you raised K10. BB is Joao, very good reg. What's your read?
테이블 4에서 K10 레이즈, BB는 주앙이네요. 아주 잘하는 레귤러인데 리딩이 어땠나요?
Yeah, solid player. Very good.
네, 견고한 스타일이죠. 아주 좋은 선수입니다.
I don't see him defending wide this deep. Are you balancing a wide c-bet range?
이 딥스택에서 넓게 방어할 것 같진 않은데, 넓은 c-bet 레인지 밸런싱인가요?
Mostly small bets happen here. It's a flush draw board.
여기선 주로 작은 벳만 나와요. 플러시 드로우 보드니까요.
He has good run outs around the 4 and 6, and a nut advantage.
4와 6 주변으로 그에게 좋은 런아웃이 많고, 넛 어드밴티지도 있습니다.
He has K6o, K4o, 64o, and we don't. So not much big betting.
그는 K6o, K4o, 64o가 있지만 우린 없죠. 그래서 큰 베팅은 잘 안 나옵니다.
Technically. But if he check-raises a quarter pot often, I'll bet half pot.
기술적으론 그렇죠. 하지만 쿼터 팟 벳에 체크 레이즈를 많이 한다면, 전 하프 팟을 벳할 겁니다.
Who is the opponent? K10 wants action but has kicker problems.
상대가 누구고 K10이 뭘 원하느냐죠. 액션은 원하지만 키커 문제가 있어요.
Folding AK? Video frozen... Oh, you added two more tables.
AK를 폴드해요? 영상이 멈췄나 보네요. 아, 테이블 두 개를 더 켰군요.
Yeah, it should go back to normal in a second. Okay, I can adjust the thing though. Hold on a sec.
네, 잠시 후면 정상으로 돌아올 겁니다. 좋아요, 제가 조정할 수 있어요. 잠시만요.
So we didn't see the size that he check-raised on the flop with, but I imagine it's like 4x or 5x?
빌런이 플랍에서 체크 레이즈한 사이즈를 못 봤는데, 아마 4x나 5x 정도였겠죠?
It's pretty easy to figure out. You bet 1.4 into 5.6 and now there's 15.6, so he made it 5 big blinds.
계산하기 쉽습니다. 5.6 팟에 1.4를 벳했고 총 15.6이 됐으니, 5bb로 레이즈한 거네요.
So again, this really comes down to player type. When you bet 25% on the flop, most high stakes regs are going to do a lot of check-raising with 6x and 4x.
다시 말하지만, 이건 플레이어 성향에 달렸습니다. 플랍에서 25% 벳을 하면, 대부분의 하이롤러 레귤러들은 6x나 4x로 체크 레이즈를 많이 할 겁니다.
In a solver, those hands are always randomizing. It's very easy for a human to not randomize 65 and just check-raise versus 25%. So it's definitely an over-bluffed node.
솔버에서는 그런 핸드들로 빈도를 섞지만(randomize), 사람은 65 같은 핸드로 25% 벳에 대해 무조건 체크 레이즈하기 쉽습니다. 그러니 분명 블러핑이 과한(over-bluffed) 노드입니다.
And then, what do you think about the turn? Would you bet or check?
그럼 턴은 어떻게 생각하세요? 벳인가요, 체크인가요?
I think he is actually going to have a lot of flush draws as well facing the smaller sizing. He's also going to have 58, 78.
작은 사이징을 상대로 빌런은 플러시 드로우도 많이 가지고 있을 겁니다. 58이나 78도 있겠죠.
But those gut-shots only have 6.6%, so it's not a big concern. I think if you go too much smaller, you might just get check-raised again.
하지만 gut-shot은 에퀴티가 6.6%밖에 안 되니 큰 걱정은 아닙니다. 너무 작게 벳하면 또 다시 체크 레이즈를 당할 위험이 있습니다.
I wouldn't mind... I think it's so unnatural for him to check value on the turn here. This is where you can actually make quite a lot of money waving the red flag.
저는 괜찮다고 봅니다. 여기서 밸류 핸드로 체크하는 건 너무 부자연스럽거든요. 오히려 약한 모습을 보여서(waving red flag) 돈을 벌 수 있는 기회입니다.
It's really tough for him to check-raise a flop with a 6 and then go for a double check-raise on the turn. You don't mind inducing here.
6을 들고 플랍 체크 레이즈를 한 뒤 턴에서 또 체크 레이즈하기는 정말 어렵습니다. 여기서 액션을 유도하는 것도 나쁘지 않습니다.
You make a lot of money because it's easy for him to over-bluff. He's kind of repping exactly 44. If you trigger something, he's likely to just have a random 4x♣️ or 75.
빌런이 과도하게 블러핑하기 쉽기 때문에 수익이 납니다. 빌런은 정확히 44를 주장하는 셈인데, 사실 랜덤한 4x♣️나 75를 가지고 있을 확률이 더 높습니다.
So he folds. Also going to go back to the AK at 42 effective. Let me get off this 4 wide screen.
빌런이 폴드했네요. 다시 42bb 유효스택 AK 핸드로 돌아가 봅시다. 화면 좀 조정할게요.
You'll notice the vast majority of people are just all-in for 40bb here with AK. And for most people, that's probably the best play.
대부분의 사람들이 여기서 AK로 그냥 40bb 올인을 박습니다. 보통 그게 가장 좋은 플레이기도 하고요.
However, when you do have such an aggressive 4-betting and bluffing image, you get to click hands like this.
하지만 공격적인 4벳과 블러핑 이미지가 있다면, 이런 핸드로 민 레이즈(click)를 할 수 있습니다.
This is 'Egyptian' the streamer. I've been coaching him for years. So he knows all about... he knows I might be light.
이 친구는 'Egyptian'이라는 스트리머인데, 제가 몇 년간 코칭했습니다. 그래서 제가 가볍게 플레이할 수도 있다는 걸 알아요.
There's definitely a non-zero percent chance he just takes A4s and he's just over it versus me here.
그가 그냥 A4s 같은 걸로 저를 상대로 밀어붙일 확률이 분명히 존재합니다.
Also what it does do, the times it goes all-in, all-in, you can probably get away then.
또한 이렇게 하면, 상대들이 줄줄이 올인 나올 때 도망갈 수 있습니다.
As in if the UTG guy shoves, and now Pat shoves with a cold 4-bet range behind, this is AA and KK only. So you can get away.
만약 UTG가 올인하고 뒤에서 Pat이 콜드 4벳으로 올인하면, 이건 AA나 KK뿐입니다. 그럼 폴드하면 되죠.
Yeah, I hadn't thought about that. Shove call, lose less, induce. Multi-faceted benefits here.
그건 생각 못 했네요. 흥미롭습니다. 올인을 콜만 따거나, 잃을 걸 줄이거나, 액션을 유도하거나. 장점이 많군요.
If he has AJo or A5s, I'm fine with those hands calling. If he starts having 78s, now it becomes dicey, now I'm more likely to shove.
상대가 AJo나 A5s라면 콜을 받아도 괜찮습니다. 만약 78s 같은 게 나온다면 위험해지니, 그때는 제가 올인하는 게 낫겠죠.
As the range gets more linear, you shove AK. And then as the range gets more polar you're facing, then you start clicking it. If he's calling AQ, I'm always shoving AK.
상대 레인지가 리니어하다면 AK로 올인합니다. 상대 레인지가 폴라하다면 민 레이즈(click)합니다. 상대가 AQ로 콜을 한다면 저는 무조건 AK로 올인합니다.
Yeah, for sure. All right, well let's end this part here, and we will see everyone in the next one.
네, 맞습니다. 그럼 이번 파트는 여기서 마치고 다음 영상에서 뵙겠습니다.